A Guide to the Office of the Attorney General Historical Files, 1938-1960
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Office of the Attorney General Historical Files, 1938-1960
The Library of Virginia
44655
2 cu. ft. (5 boxes)
Virginia Office of the Attorney General
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of Virginia, 2.2-3705.5) and the Virginia Health Records Privacy Act (Code of Virginia, 32.1-172.1:03) establish guidelines for restricting access to medical and other confidential forms of information in order to protect personal privacy. The Virginia Public Records Act (Code of Virginia, 42.1-78) includes a provision for closing all privacy protected information for 75 years from the date of creation. In accordance with this legislation, the Library of Virginia can and will restrict, in whole or in part, access to any privacy protected medical information or any other confidential information contained in these records.
Acquisition Information
Acquisition information unavailable.
Historical Information
The Office of the Attorney General originated in medieval England. While representing the king in his courts, the Attorney General gradually assumed the role of legal advisor to the government and all its agencies. In Virginia, the first Attorney General was commissioned in 1643. The Declaration of Independence in 1776 ended the Attorney General's connection with royal authority, but the state constitution adopted that year continued the office under the auspices of the General Assembly. The constitution adopted in 1851 provided for the popular election of the Attorney General, rendering him independent of all three branches of government. The Attorney General is elected to a four-year term in office and is eligible for reelection.
On April 27, 1927, the General Assembly passed a state government reorganization act that created the Department of Law, with the Attorney General serving as the chief executive officer. The Office represents the interests of the Commonwealth in civil cases in which the Commonwealth or any of its agencies or officials is named as a party, and in criminal cases on appeal to the Court of Appeals of Virginia and the Supreme Court of Virginia. In cases involving federal law, the Attorney General also represents the Commonwealth's interests. The Office also defends the constitutionality of state laws when they are challenged in court, represents consumers in utility matters before the State Corporation Commission, and collects debts owed to state agencies, hospitals and universities. Additionally, the Attorney General serves as the legal advisor to the Governor and more than 200 state agencies, boards, commissions and institutions. He renders official opinions upon the written request of the Governor, members of the General Assembly, members of the judiciary, state officials, and local constitutional officers.
Scope and Content
Restricted: Files pertaining to accounts in collection for DeJarnette State Sanatorium and Western State Hospital that are less than 75 years old. Due to the presence of restricted patient information, these records may require review by an archivist and/or redaction (if it is possible) before they are served. Contains subject files created and maintained by the Office of the Attorney General. The files were created by several different administrations, including those of Abram P. Staples, Harvey B. Apperson, J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., and Albertis S. Harrison. The files were kept and maintained because of their historical significance. Topics include a gasoline price fixing investigation conducted by the Attorney General's office, the Medical College of Virginia Hospital building, accounts in collection for DeJarnette State Sanatorium and Western State Hospital, various bills and legislation introduced in the General Assembly, civil rights legislation related to voting and the poll tax, pornography and obscenity legislation, and an amicus curiae brief filed in the Supreme Court case United States of America v. Appalachian Electric Power Company.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Historical Files, 1938-1960
Arranged alphabetically according to folder title. Correspondence and other documents within each folder are, in most cases, loosely arranged in reverse chronological order.
Contents List
- Assessment of Property Belonging to Public Service Corporations, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Blue Law Legislation (1960 General Assembly), 1959. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Board of Supervisors Compensation (House Bill 34), 1958. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bread Bill, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Condemnation Powers of Water Authority (Senator John A. K. Donovan), 1958. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- DeJarnette State Sanatorium / Western State Hospital (Accounts in Collection), 1938-1941. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- DeJarnette State Sanatorium / Western State Hospital (Accounts in Collection), 1938-1941. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- DeJarnette State Sanatorium / Western State Hospital (Accounts in Collection), 1938-1941. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- DeJarnette State Sanatorium / Western State Hospital (Accounts in Collection), 1938-1941. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Federal Voting Assistance Program (Senator Charles Fenwick), 1958. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Gasoline Price Fixing Investigation, 1940-1941. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Gasoline Price Fixing Investigation, 1940-1941. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Gasoline Price Fixing Investigation, 1940-1941. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Gasoline Price Fixing Investigation, 1940-1941. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Gasoline Price Fixing Investigation, 1940-1941. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Gasoline Price Fixing Investigation, 1940-1941. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Gasoline Price Fixing Investigation, 1940-1941. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- General Assembly (1948 Session), 1947-1948. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- General Assembly (1950 Bills), 1950. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- General Assembly (1950 Bills), 1950. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- General Assembly (1950 Session), 1949-1950. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- General Assembly (1950 Session), 1949-1950. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- General Assembly (1950 Session), 1949-1950. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- General Assembly (1950 Session), 1949-1950. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- General Assembly (1950 Session), 1949-1950. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Legal Aid Societies in Virginia (Rules and Regulations Promulgated by the Virginia State Bar), undated. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Medical College of Virginia Hospital (Building Specifications), 1939. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Medical College of Virginia Hospital (Executed Contract for Heating, Plumbing and Air Conditioning), 1939. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Medical College of Virginia Hospital (J. Slotnik Company Correspondence), 1939-1942. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Medical College of Virginia Hospital (J. Slotnik Company Correspondence), 1939-1942. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Medical College of Virginia Hospital (J. Slotnik Company Correspondence), 1939-1942. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Medical College of Virginia Hospital (J. Slotnik Company Correspondence), 1939-1942. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Medical College of Virginia Hospital (J. Slotnik Company Correspondence), 1939-1942. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Poll Tax Amendment and Civil Rights Legislation, 1959-1960. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Poll Tax Amendment and Civil Rights Legislation, 1959-1960. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Pornography and Obscenity Legislation, 1959-1960. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Pornography and Obscenity Legislation, 1959-1960. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Sales Tax Legislation (1960 General Assembly), undated. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- State Compensation Board, 1948-1949. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- State Forest Service (Accounts in Collection), 1941. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- United States vs Appalachian Electric Power Company (Amicus Curiae Brief), 1940-1941. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- United States vs Appalachian Electric Power Company (Amicus Curiae Brief), 1940-1941. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- United States vs Appalachian Electric Power Company (Amicus Curiae Brief), 1940-1941. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- United States vs Appalachian Electric Power Company (Amicus Curiae Brief), 1940-1941. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- United States vs Appalachian Electric Power Company (Amicus Curiae Brief), 1940-1941. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- United States vs Appalachian Electric Power Company (Amicus Curiae Brief / Miller Bills), 1947-1948. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Virginia Gasoline Retailers Association (Proposed 1960 Legislation), 1959. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Virginia Gasoline Retailers Association (Proposed 1960 Legislation), 1959. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- War Veterans, Division of (Discharge of Employees), undated. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Water and Sewer Project, Opinion Rendered (Hon. J.J. Williams and Hon. Minetree Folkes), undated. (Box 5, Folder 8)